Register of the Donald Marquand Dozer Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
- SPEECHES AND WRITINGS FILE, circa 1930-1980
  - "America's New Foreign Policy,", 1951 December
    - General
      - General. Letters, including one to Senator Taft, flyer, clippings, press release, speech transcripts (Robert A. Taft), 1951-1954 (Folder 14)
      - Report by the Minority Policy Committee, "Comparative Views on Foreign Policy by National Leaders," Mimeograph report, 1951 January (Folder 15)
    - Text (?) Extremely rough draft materials (Folder 16)
  - "Memorandum on the Latin American Policy of the United States," Prepared for Rep. Lawrence H. Smith. Typescript, correspondence, and draft materials, 1952 December 1952-1956 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Review of G.T. Anderson, Yankees in Ferment, Correspondence and notes, 1953 (Folder 2)
  - "Memorandum for Mr. Louis Lawrence," (assistant to Senators Taft and Watkins; SEE ALSO: CORRESPONDENCE FILE/ Lawrence, Louis), Typescript commentary on H. Chr. Sonne, "Statement on Latin America" (typescript copy attached), 1953 April (Folder 3)
  - Review of Teodoro Alvarado Garaicoa, Sinopsis del Derecho Territorial Ecuatoriano, Guayaquil, 1952, American Journal of International Law, Typescript and memorandum, 1953 October (Folder 4)
  - Review of Atilio Dell'Oro Maini, et al., La Conquista de America el Descubrimiento del Moderno Derecho Internacional: Estudios Sobre Las Ideas de Francisco de Vitoria, American Journal of International Law, Typescript and letters, 1953 October (Folder 5)
  - Untitled, Relates to Latin Americirca Typescript with correspondence, 1956 (Folder 6)
  - "The Riddle of the Parties," Typescript with cover memorandum, clippings and pamphlets relating to 1952 and 1956 political conventions, 1956 Summer (Folder 7)
  - Review of Eric F. Goldman, The Crucial Decade: America, 1945-1955, Chicago Sunday Tribune Magazine of Books, 1956 August 19 (Folder 8)
  - "History and Centralism," circa 1957. Typescript and letters, 1957-1958 (Folder 9)
  - "Lincoln's Rival at Gettysburg, 1863," 1957. Typescript and letters, 1957-1970 (Folder 10)
  - Review of J. Hampden Jackson, The World in the Postwar Decade 1945-1955, Chicago Sunday Tribune Magazine of Books, 1957 March 10 (Folder 11)
  - "The Right to Know," Newsletter of the Minute Women of the U.S.A., Inc. Printed article and letter, 1957 October-November (Folder 12)
  - "Caribbean Relations with Non-American Countries," The Caribbean: Contemporary International Relations, A.C. Wilgus (ed.), Materials from Conference on the Caribbean, University of Florida, 1957 december Typescript and correspondence, 1957-1958, 1956-1957 (Folder 13)
  - "Highlights of Maryland History," Speech transcript, 1957-1958 (Folder 14)
  - "Benjamin Harrison, President of the United States," (Dr. Dozer wrote four chapters to complete a manuscript started by Albert T. Volwiler), circa 1958
    - General
      - Correspondence, Includes applications for funding support, correspondence with the Huntingdon Library (Allan Nevins) and limited correspondence with Arthur M. Schlesinger, 1936-1975 (Folder 15-19)
      - Research materials. Preliminary inventory of the A.T. Volwiler collection of Benjamin Harrison papers, miscellany, clipping, and a typed copy of a chapter from Edward Arthur White, The Republican Party in National Politics (Folder 20)
    - Chapters (by Donald M. Dozer). Typescripts
      - 11. Favorite Son of Indiana (includes Table of Contents) (Box 16, Folder 1)
      - 12. Presidential Candidate (Folder 2)
      - 13. President-Elect (Folder 3)
      - 14. Cabinet-Making (Folder 4)
  - Review of Victor J. Fox, The Pentagon Case, Typescript, 1958 June 27 (Folder 5)
  - Untitled, Speech transcript relating to the American liberal tradition and The Pentagon Case, 1958 June 27 (Folder 6)
  - Review of Eric S. Thompson (ed.), Thomas Gage's Travels in the New World, Baltimore Sun, Clipping and letter, 1958 August 10 (Folder 7)
  - "Our South American Neighbors--What Are the Areas of Tension?" Mimeographed speech transcript, drafts, letter and clipping, 1958 September 30 and 1960 March 28 (Folder 8)
  - "Public Attitudes Affecting United States-Latin American Relations," 1959. Memoranda, draft outlines, letters, and an announcement of the project for the U.S. Senate, Foreign Relations Committee, Subcommittee on American Republic Affairs, 1958-1959 (Folder 9)
  - Are We Good Neighbors? Three Decades of Inter-American Relations, 1930-1960, University of Florida Press, Reprinted with a new introduction by Johnson Book Reprint Company, 1959. 1972 June
    - General
      - Correspondence
        - General, Primarily publishers (with some reviews), research inquiries and applications for funding, 1945-1965 (Folder 10-15)
        - Johnson Reprint Corp., 1969-1972 (Folder 16)
        - University of Florida Press
          - General, 1956-1970 (Box 17, Folder 1-3)
          - Rippy, J. Fred (primary reviewer), 1956-1960 (Folder 4)
      - Miscellaneous. Outlines, memoranda, and a fragment from a printed book (Folder 5)
      - Promotional material, 1960-1972 (Folder 6)
      - Reviews, Includes correspondence with Frederic Nelson (Saturday Evening Post), 1960-1962 (Folder 7)
      - Source material
        - Non-printed material
          - General, Memoranda, charts, lists of dispatches, letters to the editor (by Carlos Urrutia-Aparicio) and a mimeographed exchange of letters between the governments of Mexico and Guatemala relating to a fishing incident, 1946-1959 (Folder 8)
          - Newsletters. State Department (News Digest) and Foreign Broadcast Information Service (Daily Report), 1950-1953 (Folder 9)
          - Press releases (primarily State Department), 1949-1958 (Folder 10)
          - Reports, Includes Maurice Halperin, "Latin America in 1951," Jorge del Canto, "Economic Development and Financial Institutions in Chile," Juan Edgar Picado Trejos and Rodrigo Soley Carrasco, "Legal Measures to Guarantee Reimbursement of the Principal and Income on Foreign Investments in the American Countries," H. Harry Szmant, "The Latin American Nasser," and the State Department (?), "Pan Americanism and the Good Neighbor Policy," (preliminary draft), 1946-1958 (Folder 11)
          - Speech transcripts, Includes John Foster Dulles, Dwight Eisenhower, Juscelino Kubitschek, Spruille Braden, Jose Maria Lemus, Miguel Ydigoras Fuentes, Arturo Frondizi and other State Dept. and Latin American officials, 1945-1959
            - A-G (Folder 12)
            - H-Y (Box 18, Folder 1)
        - Printed material
          - General. Pamphlets, printed article, newsletters, serial issues, clippings, reports, speech transcript, 1945-1948 (Folder 2-3)
          - Articles (translated from Latin American sources), 1939-1949
            - 1939 May-1944 December (Folder 4-9)
            - 1945 January-1949 March (Box 19, Folder 1-4)
    - Foreword and Preface. Includes Introduction from reprinted version (Folder 5)
    - 1. Caliban Transfigured (Folder 6)
    - 2. Hemispheric Isolation (Folder 7)
    - 3. On the Brink of War (Folder 8)
    - 4. Partners in Wartime (Folder 9)
    - 5. "Yanqui" Traits (Folder 10)
    - 6. Weakening Partnership (Folder 11)
    - 7. Illusion and Disillusion (Box 20, Folder 1)
    - 8. New Directions in Latin America (Folder 2)
    - 9. Reaction to the Cold War (Folder 3)
    - 10. Charting the Future (Folder 4)
    - Bibliography (Folder 5)
  - "Benjamin Harrison," Encyclopaedia Britannica, Typescript, printed copy and correspondence, 1959 (Folder 6)
  - Review of Gilberto Freyre, New World in the Tropics: The Culture of Modern Brazil, Baltimore Sun, Printed copy, 1959 March 1 (Folder 7)
  - Review of Edward Tomlinson, Look Southward, Uncle: A New Look at the Other 175,000,000 Americans, Baltimore Sun, Printed copy, 1959 July 12 (Folder 8)
  - "Caribbean Crisis," circa 1960. Two typescript drafts and letters, 1960-1961 (Folder 9)
  - "The Dilemma of Our Time," Speech for UCSB History Department Lecture Series. Transcript, correspondence and clippings, 1960 February (Folder 10)
  - Voice of America Broadcast, Holograph relating to Latin American relations, 1960 March 29 (Box 21, Folder 1)
  - "Pan Americanism from the Latin American Point of View," Mimeographed speech transcript and clipping, 1960 April 15 (Folder 2)
  - "A Forward-Looking Foreign Policy," Typescript and clipping, 1960 June (Folder 3)
  - Untitled, Address to the Daughters of the American Revolution. Transcript of speech relating to American liberal and constitutional tradition, with letter, 1960 September (Folder 4)
  - Untitled, Speech at San Marcos Jr. High School. Transcript, clipping, correspondence with UCSB officials, 1960 October 1960-1961 (Folder 5)
  - Review of Richard N. Adams and Charles C. Cumberland, United States University Cooperation in Latin America, Pacific Historical Review, Reprint and letters, 1960 November (Folder 6)
  - Untitled, Speeches given in Santa Barbara to visiting Brazilians. Typescripts (E)(P) (apparently two separate speeches), clippings, letters and miscellany, 1960 November (Folder 7)
  - "The United States and Latin America--Our Political Relations and the Organization of American States," Transcript of speech given at the Institute of World Affairs meeting, with program and correspondence, 1960 December (Folder 8)
  - Review of Robert F. Smith, The United States and Cuba: Business and Diplomacy, 1917-1960, circa 1961. Typescript and letters, 1961-1962 (Folder 9)
  - Review of William Benton, The Voice of Latin America, circa 1961. Typescript with letter, 1961-1962 (Folder 10)
  - Review of E. Lieuwen, Arms and Politics in Latin America, Typescript, circa 1961 (Folder 11)
  - "Mary Lord Harrison" and "Caroline Scott Harrison," Notable American Women, 1607-1950, 1961. Typescripts, notes, clippings, correspondence, and miscellany, 1892-1961 (Folder 12)
  - "America's New Nationalism," Typescript and correspondence with Frederic Nelson, 1961 (Folder 13)
  - "Argentine Antecedents of Peronismo," Rough draft, notes, and letters, 1961 (Folder 14)
  - Review of Aubert J. Clark, The Movement for International Copyright in Nineteenth Century America, American Historical Review, Printed copy, 1961 April (Folder 15)
  - "Did the Sanctions Against Trujillo Help the U.S.A.?" Saturday Evening Post, Correspondence, including Frederic Nelson, clipping, typescript draft and printed copies, 1961 April 1 (Folder 16)
  - Review of chapters for Illustrated World History (E. Wright and K.M. Stampp, eds.), McGraw-Hill, 1962. Correspondence and mimeographed outline of proposed volume, 1962-1963 (Folder 17)
  - Review of Bryce Wood, The Making of the Good Neighbor Policy, Mississippi Valley Historical Review, Reprint and letters, 1962 March (Folder 18)
  - Untitled, Speech presented to UCSB History Department meeting. Holograph and letters, 1962 April (Folder 19)
  - Latin America: An Interpretive History, Published in a Portuguese edition, 1967; second edition published in 1980 by the University of Arizona, Center for Latin American Studies, 1962
    - General
      - Correspondence
        - General, Primarily research inquiries, requests for permission to use photographs and previously-published materials. Includes letters from the Nicaraguan Ambassador and the Embassies of Haiti and the Dominican Republic, 1960-1980 (Folder 20-22)
        - Publishers
          - General, 1957-1974 (Folder 23)
          - McGraw-Hill, 1959-1975 (Box 22, Folder 1-5)
          - University of Arizona, Center for Latin American Studies, 1979-1980 (Folder 6-7)
      - Miscellaneous. Notes, statement of purpose, citations (Folder 8)
      - Promotional material. Clippings, flyers and other miscellany (Folder 9)
      - Reviews, 1960-1963 (Folder 10)
    - First edition. Galley proofs
      - Preface, Bibliographical Note, Table of Contents (Folder 11)
      - 1. Latin America in Perspective (Folder 12)
      - 2. New World, New Horizons (Folder 13)
      - 3. Southward the Course of Empire (Folder 14)
      - 4. The Foreign Challenge (Folder 15)
      - 5. The Structure of Imperial Government (Folder 16)
      - 6. Indian and African (Folder 17)
      - 7. Ways of Life (Folder 18)
      - 8. Apogee of Centralism (Folder 19)
      - 9. Twilight of Empire (Box 23, Folder 1)
      - 10. The Winning of Independence (Folder 2)
      - 11. Organizing New Nations (Folder 3)
      - 12. Emerging Governments in Southern South America (Folder 4)
      - 13. Defending their Nationality (Folder 5)
      - 14. Constitutionalism versus Personalism (Folder 6)
      - 15. The Struggle for Liberalismm (Folder 7)
      - 16. The Triumph of Republicanism in Brazil (Folder 8)
      - 17. The Consolidation of Liberalism (Folder 9)
      - 18. Conservative Reaction (Folder 10)
      - 19. Latin America and the Imperialism of the United States (Folder 11)
      - 20. The New Liberalism (Folder 12)
      - 21. New International Complications (Folder 13)
      - 22. Limitations of Liberalism in the Twentieth Century (Folder 14)
      - 23. Social Democracy versus National Socialism (Folder 15)
      - 24. War and Postwar Problems (Folder 16)
      - 25. Latin America in the Contemporary World (Folder 17)
      - Appendices (Folder 18)
      - Index (Folder 19)
    - Revised edition (not published)
      - Preface and Bibliographical Note (revised) (Folder 20)
      - Chapters 1-11 (revised) (Folder 21-31)
      - Chapters 12-14 (revised) (Box 24, Folder 1-13)
      - 25. Quest for Social Justice (new chapter) (Folder 14)
      - 26. The Shibboleth of Development (new chapter) (Folder 15)
      - 27. National and International Politics (new chapter) (Folder 16)
      - Appendices (revised) (Folder 17)
      - Index (revised) (Folder 18)
  - "Thomas Jefferson and the Making of the Constitution," Speech transcript and letters, 1963 January 3. 1962-1963 (Folder 19)
  - Review of Robert J. Alexander, Today's Latin America, Annals of the American Academy of Political and Social Science, Mimeographed article and letters, 1963 December 1962-1963 (Folder 20)
  - Review of C.N. Ronning, Law and Politics in American Diplomacy, Typescript and letter, 1964 May. 1963-1964 (Folder 21)
  - "The Problem of Recognition Historically Considered," 1964 october 24. Paper presented at Pacific Coast Council on Latin American Studies, San Diego State University; subsequently published as "Recognition in Contemporary Inter-American Relations," Journal of Inter-American Studies, 1966 April
    - Speech transcript and correspondence, Relates primarily to the organization of the conference and includes typescript of Paul E. Hadley, "Multilateral Recognition Policies in the Inter-American System", 1963-1964 (Folder 22)
    - Draft article and correspondence, Includes reviews, press release, and clippings, 1964-1966 (Folder 23)
  - "New Horizons for the United States in World Affairs," Graduate Institute for World Affairs, Fourth Annual Conference, Ohio State University. Includes agenda, correspondence, a mimeographed copy of John J. Johnson, "Independencia and the Future of United States-Latin American Relations," and a typescript of Dr. Dozer's presentation of a commentary on this report, 1964 November (Folder 24)
  - Untitled, Transcript of a commencement address and clipping, 1964 December 18 (Box 25, Folder 1)
  - "Our Canal in Panama," Typescript and letters, 1964-1965 (Folder 2)
  - "The Interoceanic Canal Problem in the Americas," and "The Contemporary Significance of the Monroe Doctrine," Latin America: Politics, Economics and Hemispheric Security, Norman A. Bailey (ed.), Report of the Center for Strategic Studies conference on The Stategic Importance of Latin America, 1964 July 17-21 (SEE ALSO: LATIN AMERICAN SUBJECT FILE/General/Inter-American Relations/United States/General/Center for Strategic Studies Colloquium), 1964-1965
    - General. Mimeographed and printed copies, press release, review, clippings, schedule and miscellaneous materials for a Georgetown University Forum radio broadcast (Folder 3)
    - Correspondence, Includes a review of this book done by Dr. Dozer for the Lilly Endowment, Inc. (Kenneth Templeton), in conjunction with a review of another book, Joseph W. Reidy, Strategy for the Americas, which is included here, 1961-1967 (Folder 4-6)
    - Texts. Mimeographed and printed copies (Folder 7-8)
  - The Monroe Doctrine: Its Modern Significance, Revised edition printed by the University of Arizona Press, 1965. 1976
    - General
      - Correspondence, 1962-1977
        - General. Primarily requests to reprint and research inquiries (Folder 9)
        - Alfred A. Knopf, Inc. (Folder 10)
        - Hanke, Lewis (series editor) (Folder 11)
        - University of Arizona, Center for Latin American Studies (Folder 12)
      - Reviews and promotional material, 1965-1967 (Folder 13)
      - Source material, 1823-1971
        - General. Pamphlets, flyer, form letter, notes, newsletter (Folder 14)
        - Articles. Mimeographed copies of clippings, book excerpts, and serial articles from Latin American, United States, and Russian sources (Box 26, Folder 1-5)
        - Statements. United States and Latin American government officials (Folder 6)
    - Introduction (to revised edition). Also includes proof fragments and miscellany (Folder 7)
    - Chapters. Mimeographed copies of articles included in the subsequently compilation
      - 1. Roque Saenz Pena, "A Doctrine of Intervention" (Folder 8)
      - 2. Manuel de la Plaza, "A Spanish View" (Folder 9)
      - 3. Carlos Pereyra, "The Three Monroe Doctrines" (Folder 10)
      - 5. Jose Ingenieros, "Need for a Pan-American Union (Folder 11)
      - 7. Baltasar Brun, "A Defensive Alliance for the Americas" (Folder 12)
      - 10. Simon Planas-Suarez, "An All-American Doctrine" (Folder 13)
      - 12. J. Reuben Clark, "Memorandum on the Monroe Doctrine" (Folder 14)
      - 15. Charles G. Fenwick, "Canada and the Monroe Doctrine" (Folder 15)
      - 17. Dexter Perkins, "The Monroe Doctrine in World War II" (Folder 16)
      - 18. Carlos Saavedra Lamas, "Economic Monroeism" (Folder 17)
      - 21. Danton Jobim, "An International Agreement" (Folder 18)
      - 23. Simon Planas-Suarez, "The Monroe Doctrine and Pan-americanism" (Folder 19)
      - 26. Basil Dmytryshyn and Jesse L. Gilmore, "The Monroe Doctrine: A Soviet View" (Folder 20)
  - "Socialist Revolution in Latin America," Trouble Abroad, Correspondence, clippings, typescript draft, 1965 (Box 27, Folder 1)
  - Review of John J. Johnson (Ed.), Continuity and Change in Latin America, Inter-American Review of Bibliography, Printed article and correspondence, 1965 (Folder 2)
  - Television broadcast in Spanish (Peru), Typed transcript relating to economic development, 1965 July 14 (Folder 3)
  - "Abandonment of Panama Canal Would Solve No Problem," Human Events, Printed article, letters, 1965 October 7 (Folder 4)
  - "History as Force," Pacific Historical Review, Also given as a speech in Buenos Aires, 1971, and reprinted by the Institute for Humane Studies, 1978. Printed article, transcript (S), pamphlet, including an earlier draft; also correspondence and clippings, 1965 November (Folder 5)
  - "Panama Canal Seen Red Strategic Aim," Printed copy, clippings, letter, 1966 June (Folder 6)
  - "The New Liberalism: Its Evolution and Characteristics," Speech transcript, 1966 June (Folder 7)
  - Review of John D. Martz, Accion Democratica: Evolution of a Modern Political Party in Venezuela, The Annals of the American Academy of Political and Social Science, Typescript and letters, 1966 September (Folder 8)
  - "The Radical Right," Speech transcript, program and clippings, 1966 November (Folder 9)
  - "History of Inter-American Relations," Correspondence course prepared for the University of California, Berkeley, Extension, circa 1967
    - Correspondence, 1964-1973 (Folder 10)
    - Text. Mimeographed copy (Folder 11)
  - "International Conferences of the Organization of American States," Compiled by Donald Dozer and Robert W. Righter. Typescript, circa 1967
    - General
      - Correspondence. Includes Dante B. Fascell, the Organization of American States (William Sanders and others), and Arnaldo T. Musich (Argentine Ambassador to U.S.), 1960-1976 (Folder 12-14)
      - Grant application, 1975-1976 (Folder 15)
    - Introduction and Table of Contents (Folder 16)
    - Volume One
      - Inter-American Conference on Conservation of Renewable Natural Resources, 1948 September 7-20 (Folder 17)
      - Third Inter-American Travel Congress, 1949 February 15-24 (Box 28, Folder 1)
      - American Committee on Dependent Territories, 1949 March 15-July 21 (Folder 2)
      - Fourth Inter-American Radio Conference, 1949 April 25-July 19 (Folder 3)
      - Second Inter-American Indian Conference, 1949 June 24-July 4 (Folder 4)
      - Special Assembly of the Inter-American Commission of Women, 1949 August 8-24 (Folder 5)
      - Second Inter-American Statistical Congress, 1950 January 16-27 (Folder 6)
      - First Inter-American Council of Jurists, 1950 May 22-June 15 (Folder 7)
      - Thirteenth Pan American Sanitary Organization, 1950 October 1-10 (Folder 8)
      - Pan American Institute of Geography and History, 1950 October 16-27 (Folder 9)
      - Fourth Inter-American Conference on Agriculture, 1950 December 1-12 (Folder 10)
      - Fourth Meeting of Consultation of Minutes of Foreign Affairs, 1951 March 26-April 7 (Folder 11)
      - Inter-American Commission of Women, 1951 May 31-June 16 (Folder 12)
      - First Inter-American Cultural Council, 1951 September 10-25 (Folder 13)
    - Volume Two
      - Fifth Pan American Highway Congress, 1951 October 7-15 (Folder 14)
      - Fourth Inter-American Travel Congress, 1952 April 12-20 (Folder 15)
      - Eighth Assembly of the Inter-American Commission of Women, 1952 July 23-August 8 (Folder 16)
      - Third Pan American Consultation on Geography, 1952 July 25-August 4 (Folder 17)
      - Special Pan American Highway Congress, 1952 October 26-November 1 (Folder 18)
      - Second Inter-American Council of Jurists, 1953 April 20-May 9 (Folder 19)
      - Ninth Inter-American Commission of Women, 1953 September 7-23 (Box 29, Folder 1)
      - Fifth Inter-American Travel Congress, 1954 June 12-19 (Folder 2)
      - Sixth Pan-American Highway Conference, 1954 July 11-23 (Folder 3)
      - Third Inter-American Indian Conference, 1954 August 2-12 (Folder 4)
      - Fourteenth Pan American Sanitary Conference, 1954 October 17-22 (Folder 5)
      - Tenth Pan America Child Congress, 1955 February 6-12 (Folder 6)
      - Tenth Inter-American Commission of Women, 1955 May 29-June 16 (Folder 7)
      - Third Meeting of the Inter-American Council of Jurists, 1956 January 17-February 4 (Folder 8)
    - Volume Three
      - Specialized Conference on "Conservation of Natural Resources: The Continental Shelf and Marine Waters,", 1956 March 15-28 (Folder 9)
      - Sixth Inter-American Travel Conference, 1956 April 14-21 (Folder 10)
      - Inter-American Port and Harbor Conference, 1956 April 25-May 3 (Folder 11)
      - Second Inter-American Meeting of Ministers of Education, 1956 May 3-9 (Folder 12)
      - The Second Meeting of the Inter-American Cultural Council, 1956 May 3-12 (Folder 13)
      - Eleventh Assembly of the Inter-American Commission of Women, 1956 June 2-21 (Folder 14)
      - Twelfth Assembly of the Inter-American Commission of Women, 1957 June 1-18 (Folder 15)
      - Seventh Pan American Highway Congress, 1957 August 1-10 (Folder 16)
      - Economic Conference of the Organization of American States, 1957 August 15-September 4 (Folder 17)
      - Fifteenth Pan American Sanitary Conference, 1958 September 21-October 3 (Box 30, Folder 1)
      - Seventh Inter-American Travel Congress, 1958 December 9-17 (Folder 2)
    - Volume Four